Ankur Jain

Principal Engineer (Director) at Google

Summary

Designed and implemented the first Google Global Cache (GGC, a CDN platform embedded in operator networks). Over time, led Google's Content Delivery Network (CDN) efforts including GGC and oversaw the CDN grow its scale several orders of magnitude into one of the largest in the world with GGC deployed today by several hundreds of carriers globally. Instrumental in bringing Software Defined Networking (SDN) and Network Function Virtualization (NFV) concepts to Google's traffic engineering and edge networking infrastructure. Leading projects over the last few years that enable wireless operators to run their networks more efficiently.

I'm also on the board of the open-source project CORD which aims to bring datacenter economics and cloud agility to the Telco Central Office. I hold more than a dozen patents and conference papers filed/granted/published. My closest potential shot at stardom though was when I went to Los Angeles in 2013 as part of the team that collected the 65th Primetime Emmy Engineering Award for YouTube; but a couple of years later I am still at Google:P

Domain Expertise: Connectivity, Internet access, Wireless, CDN, Content Distribution, SDN, Wireless Performance, Mapping, TCP, Caching, DNS, Load Balancing, Large-scale Distributed Systems, Networking, Internet Measurements, Routing.

Functions: Engineering lead. Centrally involved in product, strategy, project management and partnerships.

Experience

Principal Engineer at Google

June 2005 - Present

Connectivity (2013 onwards) -

https://blog.google/topics/internet-access/partnering-toward-next-generation-mobile-networks/

https://youtube-eng.googleblog.com/2016/04/announcing-mobile-data-plan-api.html

https://policybythenumbers.googleblog.com/2015/09/information-sharing-for-more-efficient.html

http://onosproject.org/2016/07/26/on-lab-and-the-linux-foundation-form-cord-project-to-define-the-future-of-access/

https://blog.google/topics/internet-access/bringing-the-internet-to-more-indians/

http://www.gadgetsnow.com/sundar-pichai-at-iit-kharagpur-toi-travels-with-google-ceo-sundar-pichai-to-iit-kharagpur/liveblog/56347635.cms#clschng56351587

Software Defined Networking/Network Virtualization (2011 onwards) -

https://www.theregister.co.uk/2017/04/04/google_serves_espresso_linkups_for_cloud/

https://blog.google/topics/google-cloud/making-google-cloud-faster-more-available-and-cost-effective-extending-sdn-public-internet-espresso/

https://blog.google/topics/internet-access/partnering-toward-next-generation-mobile-networks/

Content Delivery (2005 - 2014) -

https://peering.google.com/#/infrastructure

http://www.emmys.com/news/press-releases/winners-announced-65th-primetime-emmy-engineering-awards

Education

University of Washington

M.S., Computer Science and Engineering, 2003 - 2005

Indian Institute of Technology, Delhi

B Tech, Computer Science and Engineering, 1999 - 2003

Ankur Jain

Principal Engineer (Director) at Google



Contact Ankur on LinkedIn